<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Letter from the government of Algier to Admiral Russell</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87976</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1521A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R43687</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">42475097</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 42475097</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151229</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87976)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151229)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2251:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Letter from the government of Algier to Admiral Russell</title>
                  <author>Ibrāhīm.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Tho. Hodgkin, and are to be sold by J. Whitlock ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: Ibrahim.</note>
                  <note>Dated in ms. on recto: 10. Sept. 1695.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Newberry Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Orford, Edward Russell, --  Earl of, 1653-1727.</term>
               <term>Grand Alliance, War of the, 1689-1697 --  Campaigns, Naval.</term>
               <term>Algeria --  Relations --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Relations --  Algeria --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  London (England) --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:151229:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 40 -->
            <head>A LETTER FROM THE Government of <hi>Algier,</hi> TO ADMIRAL <hi>RUSSELL.</hi> 
               <date>
                  <add>10. Sept. 1695.</add>
               </date>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <signed>THE Vice-Governour, <hi>Ibrahim Effendi,</hi> with all the <hi>Divan,</hi>
               </signed>
               <salute>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutation to the Famous Admiral, and moſt Valiant General, our dear and well-beloved true Friend, the Renowned Mr. <hi>Ruſſell,</hi> ſo highly Eſteem'd by that great Chriſtian King, whoſe Kingdom is wiſely Govern'd.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Theſe are to give you to underſtand, that it is impoſſible for Tongue to Expreſs, or Pen to Write, the Friendſhip we have for You; We pray to God Almighty, that your, and our Enemies may be ſpeedily brought under ſuch Afflictions and Troubles, that they may never be able to riſe up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us, and we deſire our Love may always encreaſe: Thanks be to God, you are this Year come into the <hi>Mediterranean,</hi> which gives us much Joy. The Ships you ſent to us are come in Safety, and the Captain your Servant, with the Conſul, who always Exalts your Fame, brought us your Letter into the <hi>Divan,</hi> which gave us the Aſſurance of the Friendſhip of that Great King, and Your Excellency to us; after which we cauſed our Caſtle to Salute him, which made thoſe that Love you Rejoyce, and our Enemies to burſt with Vexation. We all know the <hi>Engliſh</hi> are, and ever were, our beſt Friends, and we pray to God to keep you and us from all Diſaſters: We were very Joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full at the appearance of Their Majeſty's Ships, and as often as you can, we deſire to ſee more of them, which will be very Pleaſing to us. This your Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain is a Man of Great Wiſdom and Conduct, and we eſteem his Courteſie and good Behaviour; but we could not ſhew him that Kindneſs which is due to him: You are to know that our Succeſsful Governour, and Maſter, is now beſieging <hi>Tunis,</hi> with Thirty Thouſand Men, his Abſence is the Reaſon of it, which we pray you not to take in evil Part; but as ſoon as it pleaſeth God he returns with Victory, we know his Favour to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> will be Great. You likewiſe give us to underſtand that His Majeſty has granted our Deſire in appointing Mr. <hi>Robert Cole</hi> (a Man well known) to be His <hi>Agent and Conſul with us,</hi> and that our old Friend Mr. <hi>Baker</hi> was ordered to return home in Their Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty's Ship; this we aſſent to with our Head and Heart; but He being our Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsful Governour's approved Friend, cannot now go, without ſeeing him; it may be on his Return to this City, our Governour may ſend to the King of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> News and Letters, and ſhow ſome more Friendſhip: In Forty or Fifty Days we expect him; though the Conſul is very willing to be gone, we all deſire him to wait our Governour's coming, and he ſhall not want a Ship of our own at his Service, if their be none of His Majeſty's Ships waiting for him; and we hope you will not be diſpleaſed, becauſe his farther ſmall ſtay may be for the
<pb facs="tcp:151229:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 41 -->
Service of his Maſter and our Benefit, and we hope hereafter it may be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to you, and cauſe great Troubles to your Enemies. We thank you for your Kindneſs in giving protection to Our Ship againſt thoſe of the <hi>Dutch,</hi> which are under your Command, we own the Favour and deſire God Almighty's Bleſſing on you for it; they alſo were good Friends to us heretofore, until ſome wicked <hi>French-Man</hi> raiſed and fomented the War, that ſtill continues; but the Time will come, if our good Friend the King of <hi>England</hi> Continue in this World, (which God Almighty grant) when we ſhall renew our Former Brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Kindneſs; Nor is War a ſtrange thing, ſince there are more Troubles than Pleaſures; but if the <hi>Dutch</hi> ſhould be obedient to the King of <hi>England,</hi> and ſhew us Favour, it may be by the Help of God hereafter for their Good, and the Love the King of <hi>England</hi> bears to you and us, and we to His Majeſty and You, may it remain in Truth for ever, <hi>Amen:</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>And ſo we leave you in the Peace of God,</salute>
               <dateline>
                  <date>the 15<hi>th.</hi> Day of the Moon <hi>Mahorran,</hi> in the Year 1106.</date>
From our Palace in the Famous City of <hi>Algier,</hi> in <hi>Barbary.</hi>
               </dateline>
               <signed>IBRAHIM.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>If it pleaſe God Almighty, <hi>This</hi> to be deliver'd into the Hands of the Famous and Valiant General, under the King of <hi>England.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Have ſent you a great many Preſents of this Sort, but underſtand they have moſt of them ſtopt by the way, at <hi>Breſt</hi> or St. <hi>Maloes.</hi> I will not think my Letters ſo miſcarried, to be altogether loſt; becauſe it is not amiſs, that our <hi>Enemies</hi> as well as <hi>Friends,</hi> ſhould know what Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Advantage the <hi>Confederates</hi> reap by the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> Fleet's choaking the <hi>Streights.</hi> This <hi>Letter</hi> came from a <hi>Barbarian,</hi> but that which brought it, will alſo bring Ambaſſadors and Letters from the fine and ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil <hi>Italians,</hi> as it has already Security to <hi>Catalonia,</hi> and Thanks from all <hi>Spain;</hi> it has lately demoliſh'd <hi>Cazal,</hi> and it may do as much to other Fortreſſes. In a Word, the Party of <hi>Dolphinizing Spaniards,</hi> was very great, and <hi>Barcellona</hi> in a very ill Condition, before our Arrival; but we have open'd their Eyes, and given them new Life, and made them good and able Subjects again. The Bombardments of St. <hi>Maloe, Granville,</hi> and <hi>Calais,</hi> are owing to our Fleets riding in the <hi>Mediterranean,</hi> and ſo will the ſafe Arrival of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Fleet, whene'er it happens. I think this is enough to ſhew that our Continuance in theſe Seas, breeds ſomething elſe beſides <hi>Worms</hi> in the King's Ships, from which I wiſh the <hi>Heads</hi> of your great <hi>Politicians</hi> were as free;</p>
            <closer>And ſo I conclude, 
<signed>your humble Servant, to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, if you could get me a Ship.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>Tho. Hodgkin,</hi> and are to be Sold by <hi>J. Whitlock</hi> near <hi>Stationers-Hall,</hi> 1695.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
